阁下果然是信人
So you've kept your promise
三位今天约我到这儿来
Why the three of you
有何见教？
want to meet me here?
你为什么杀我们四弟？
Why did you kill our fourth brother?
这倒怪了
That's strange
当时约我决斗的是你们四弟
Your fourth brother asked me to have a duel
难道我只输得而赢不得吗？
And I could only be defeated and can't win, right?
那你也用不着致他于死地
But you didn't have to kill him
要是我只伤了他
Well, if I just injured him...
你们三位不又怪我
then you would blame me for insulting
辱没你们中州四剑的威名吗？
the name of Four Swords of Zhongzhou
丁梦豪，你别仗着你的剑法高强
Ding Menghao, you can't just hurt others
就任意伤害江湖剑手
with your sword because you have good skills
你以为天下第一剑手这个称号
Do you think you can keep the title
会是永远的吗？
"Fastest Sword" forever?
你们是看不惯我
Are you jealous of me
还是看不惯我的剑？
or my prowess with the sword?
不错，我们兄弟三人倒要领教
Well, let's find this out
好剑法
Excellent skills
好是好，不过火候还不够
It's good, but not refined enough
老家伙，你说什么？
Old man, what are you saying?
你跟他们有仇吗？
You have a grudge with them?
你管这个干什么？
It's none of your business
江湖传言丁梦豪出剑无情
Rumour has it that you're a ruthless killer
今日一见果然名不虚传
Now I know it is true
我很欣赏你的剑法
I admire your sword skills
不过要称天下第一剑嘛
But you don't really deserve the title
还早了点
'The Fastest Sword' yet
你不服？
So you're not convinced?
慢着，慢着
Wait, wait
如果你要想跟我动手的话
I don't mind having a duel with you
干脆咱们先把话讲清楚了
Let's however make things clear
再打也不迟
before we have a duel
有话快说
Sure, tell me
如果你输给我怎么办？
What if you were defeated?
可能吗？
Is it possible?
我也知道不可能
Even I know it's impossible
我是说万一的话
I mean, just in case you were
那废话嘛
Rubbish
我输了你当然杀了我
If I were defeated you would kill me for sure
还不成呀？
You are not satisfied with it?
难道你要把我身上的肉
So you want to cut me dead
一块块的割下来？
piece by piece?
都不是，我这个人正好跟你相反
No, I am not like you
生平最不喜欢杀人
I don't like killing people
那你要怎么样？
So what do you want?
干干脆脆的把话说出来
Simply speak it out
这样吧
Okay
如果你要是败在我的烟杆之下
If you were defeated by my smoking pipe
你就得跟我三年，在这三年之内
You'd have to stay with me for three years
我要你干什么，你就得给我干什么
And do whatever I tell you to do
那我也改变主意了
Then I've a change of mind too
我也不杀你，你也得跟我三年
You also have to stay with me for three years
做我跟班，替我背行李
You'll be my servant and carry my belongings
我都是八十岁的人了
I am an eighty-year-old man
给你做跟班，不嫌老了点吗？
Don't you think I'm a bit old to be your servant?
我就喜欢你这个样子
Well, I like that
好，那是你答应了
Alright, so it is a deal
好，咱们动手，来
Okay, come on
慢着，你还打什么？
Wait, no need to fight anymore
你看看你的胸前
Take a look at your chest
乖乖的跟我走吧
So you come with me now
喂，喂
Hey, hey
师傅，师傅
Master, master
老家伙
Old guy!
你忘了我们的约定了吗？
You forgot our deal?
要是忘了，我早就跑了
If I did I'd be gone long time ago
那么就好好的坐在这儿
Then keep sitting here quietly
师傅，你既然要折磨我
Master, if you want to torture me
换个花样好不好？
please find another way to do it, okay?
这半年坐下来
I've been sitting here for half a year
坐得我腰酸背痛
I've almost got a back pain
你要想做些什么呢？
Then what do you want to do?
随你的便
Anything
只要手脚能够活动活动就行了
Only if I could stretch my hands and legs
也好，我就给你换个样子
Okay, I'll let you do something else
你给我把这些经书一本本的抄完它
Copy all the scriptures in this room
然后一张一张的粘起来
then paste the copies one by one
转到这个木盘上面
and wind them around this wheel
抄完了再下楼来见我
Come down to see me after you've finished
抄完它？
All of them?
怎么，不愿意？
What? Don't want to do it?
不愿意就跟我下楼去打坐，走
Then come and meditate with me. Let's go
好，好，我愿意，愿意
Okay, okay, I'll do it
师傅
Master
怎么，抄完啦？
What? Finished?
那么快呀？
So fast?
你上去看看就知道
Go take a look upstairs.
好
Okay
真快
Really fast
这个法子倒不错
This is a smart way
不过，你知道吗？
But do you know that
你的手指没有起茧
you don't have callus on your fingers
你的眼睛里面空空洞洞的
and your eyes look empty
就跟这卷白纸一样
They're just like this roll of white paper
外表好看，里面是什么也没有
Looks nice but it's nothing inside
我再抄下去眼睛都看不见了
I'll be blind if I keep copying
有些事情用心比用眼睛看
Sometimes you can see more clearly
是更清楚，更明白，你说是不是
with your mind, not your eyes, right?
师傅，我不是这种料
Master, I'm not that type of person
您白费力气
You would waste your effort
那么你说你是什么料呢？
So what type of a person are you?
我什么料都不是
I'm just nothing
现在懂得点谦虚了
Now you're starting to know what humility is
好了，好了
Okay, okay
别说风凉话了
Cut the crap
您就让我去挑土，砍柴
Just let me collect dirt, or cut firewood
什么粗活都行
I don't care if it is tough work
手里不抓个家伙，就缺少什么事
I'm lost if I don't have a tool in my hand
好吧，跟我来
Fine, follow me
做什么用？
What is this for?
你看见那块大石头了吗？
See that big rock?
把它敲掉？
Want me to knock it into pieces?
不过要敲成个东西
No, you have to make something out of it
什么东西？
What?
随你便
Whatever you want
你爱敲什么就敲什么
Just make it into something you like
现在我要下山去走走
Now I'll go downhill
半年以后我再回来看你
I'll be back six months later
好手艺
Very good skill
师傅
Master
你辛苦了
You've been working hard
您看怎么样？
What do you think?
好是好，不过…
It's very good, but...
怎么，您还不满意？
What? You don't like it?
不是不满意，只是太大了一点
Not really, it's just a bit too big
而且你让如来佛坐在山门旁边
Besides, don't you think it isn't very appropriate
不过份了点吗？
to put a Buddha in front of the door?
这样吧，你改一改
Well, make some changes
我下山去办点事
I have to leave here now
半年以后咱们再见
See you six months later
师傅，您回来了
Master, you are back
不错，进步多了
Not bad, you have improved
不过…
But...
又太大了？
Too big again?
再改小点
Make it smaller
您这样一次次的改
You've made me change the size again and again
你急什么？
What's the hurry?
还有半年的时间呢
We still have another half year
好吧，您下您的山吧
Alright, you can leave now
我这次一定让您满意
I'm sure you'll be satisfied this time
好极了，好一个玉面金刚
Excellent, what a beautiful statue
您想要的原来就是这个东西？
So this is what you want?
不错
That's right
您怎么不早说呢？
Then why didn't you tell me early?
让我花两三年的时间去雕石头
I've been spending years in stone carving
你认为不值得吗？你知道吗？
So you think it's not worth it?
如果你改行做雕工的话
If you took stone carving as a profession
将来你一定是一个名家的
you would be a famous craftsman
多谢师傅指点
Master, thanks for your teaching
我可以下山了吗？
Can I leave now?
你急什么？
What's the hurry?
我还要送给你一句话
I have one more thing to tell you
什么话？
What's that?
如果你想活的话
If you want to live
你一定要死一次
You have to die once
那我就不懂了
I don't quite understand this
你将来会懂的，去吧
You will. Now leave
告辞了
Goodbye
"Chu's Drill Ground"
你都已经输了，还打什么？
You're defeated, why keep fighting?
丁老弟，又死了一个？
Brother Ding, another one died?
师傅
Master
他到我们馆里来才两个多月
He's been here for less than three months
已经有十来个人
And more than a dozen people
死在他的剑下
were killed by his sword
以后还多着呢
There will be more in the future
请问这位师傅…
Master, may I ask...
您是？
You are?
听说天下第一剑手丁梦豪
I've heard that the Fastest Sword, Ding Menghao,
就在这个馆里？
is in this place
你找他干什么？
Why are you looking for him?
比剑
To have a duel
比剑？你没看见这位英雄
A duel? Don't you see this man
刚刚死在他的剑下？
has just been killed by his sword?
你少嗦，他在哪儿？
Cut the crap. Where's he now?
上酒店喝酒去了
Go for a drink in the inn
您吃什么？
What do you want?
大爷，您楼上请
Sir, please go upstairs
掌柜的，有人来找他了
Boss, someone is looking for him
赶快收拾东西
Let's hide our stuff
阁下有何见教？
What do you want from me?
你就是被江湖黑白道上称为
So are you Ding Menghao,
天下第一剑手的南剑
the Southern Sword who is regarded by everyone
丁梦豪丁大侠吗？
as the Fastest Sword?
在下就是，请教…
Yes, I am, and you are?
金剑帮少帮主毕正文久仰阁下大名
Bi Zhengwan from Golden Sword Clan
今天专程一会
I'm here only to meet you
毕兄何不坐下共饮一杯
Sit down and let's have a drink together
我的话你还没答覆呢
You haven't answered me yet
我跟少帮主并无冤仇
There's no enmity between you and me
谁跟你有冤仇？
That's for sure
我只是来领教你的剑法
I just come to have a duel with you
要是我胜了你
If I won the duel
我就是天下第一剑手
I would be the Fastest Sword in the world
少帮主，在下只是徒负虚名
I really don't deserve such a title
你还是去找北剑邱一星吧
Go and look for Qiu Yixing, the Northern Sword
北剑邱一星，他算什么？
Qiu Yixing the Northern Sword? He's nothing
我不跟你比剑
I won't have a duel with you
难道我不配？
Am I not qualified?
少帮主今年贵庚？
How old are you?
十八岁，这跟比剑有什么关系？
Eighteen. Why? It has nothing to do with a duel
当然有关系
Of course it does
所谓刀剑无情
Weapons are ruthless
丁某如败在你剑下并不可惜
If I were defeated, it's not a shame
少帮主年纪还轻，前程似锦
But you are still young, you have a future
你少教训我，拔剑
Don't preach. Draw your sword
你真不肯？
So you really refuse me?
现在动手吧
Let's have a duel now
给我上帐
I'll pay later
我就不信你不出手
I'm sure you will have a duel with me
站住，丁大侠
Stop, Master Ding
你再不出手，别怪我无礼了
Don't blame me if you still keep refusing
我早告诉过你不跟你比
I've told you I don't want to fight with you
还想要什么？
So what do you want?
告诉你
Let me tell you
我要天下第一剑手六个字
I want these words: The Fastest Sword
你别误会，我根本不是
You've made a mistake. I am not
这小子真会找死
This kid is only here to meet his death
丁老弟
Brother Ding
师傅
Master
不瞒你说，自从你到我们寨上
Honestly, since you came to our village
可以说是没有一天安宁过
there's no peace here
所以父老们的意思
So the seniors suggested
希望你能够换一个地方
you should go somewhere else
这件事…
lt...
我知道
I understand
要不是虚名累我，何至于此呢？
It's all because I'm bearing an illusory title
他也死得太年轻
He died too young
其实我不想杀他
Actually I didn't intend to kill him
也不想杀任何人
Nor anyone else for that matter
这是大家给你凑的一点盘缠
We've gathered some money for you
我走好了，谢谢师傅
I'll leave now. Master, thank you
师傅请了
Master
这位壮士有何见教？
Anything I can help you with?
不敢，在下是来打听一个人
I am looking for someone
丁梦豪，找他比剑？
Are you looking for Ding Menghao, to have a duel?
我是要找丁梦豪
Yes, I'm looking for him
不过我是他的朋友
But I am his friend
他已经走了
He has left
走了？
Left?
走了好几天了，请
It's been several days. Goodbye
"Qing Feng Fortress"
各位好…
Hello, everybody...
掌柜，您回来了？
Boss, you're back
你怎么老是管我叫掌柜的？
Stop calling me boss
张老弟
Brother Zhang
我们柳家寨的人都叫我柳大虎
Everyone here calls me Liu Da Fu
你叫我一声柳大哥不就行了吗？
You can just call me Brother Liu
是，柳大哥
Yes, Brother Liu
观音像什么时候完工？
When are you going to finish the Guanyin statue?
后天就可以交货
Day after tomorrow
不要紧，慢慢的刻吧
It's okay, take your time
把这个给我
Give this to me
伙计
Waiter
大爷
Yes, sir
您是要住店还是？
Do you want a room or?
住店
I want a room
好，里面有雅房，请
Alright, we have nice rooms here, please
你们先吃饭，把家伙打点一下
Go get something to eat first
我去向柳庄主讨个人情就回来
I'm going to ask Master Liu a favour
王生，您太客气了
Wang Sang, you're too kind
一点薄礼，实在不成敬意
Just a little gift
希望庄主行个方便
I want to ask you a favour
给老朽在庄子上摆个场子
Please let me set up a vendor booth in your village
你尽管做就是了
That's no problem
柳东，把礼收下
Liu Dong, take the gifts inside
赏给他二两银子
And give him a silver nugget
这怎么可以？
No need
庄主肯让老朽摆个场
I should be very grateful to have your permission
老朽已经感激不尽
to set up a vendor booth
都是道上朋友，收下收下
We are friends. Take it
恭敬不如从命
Okay, if you insist
多谢庄主厚赐
Thank you very much.
请
Goodbye
老朽告辞
I have to go, goodbye
柳东，刚才你说什么？
Liu Dong, what did you say just then?
您知道我们庄上的那间雕刻店？
You know that stone carving shop in our village?
你说大虎呀，他怎么啦？
You mean Da Fu? How's he doing?
听说大虎店里来了个年轻的石匠
Da Fu's shop has a new mason recently
手艺好，可是人很怪
Very good skill, but a bit strange
他平时就难得说一句话
He seldom utters a word
而且就连大门口都不迈出一步
and never leaves the shop
他进庄的时候
When he came to our village
还有人看见他带了一把很好的剑
Someone saw him with a very good sword
您看他会不会是…？
Do you think he might be?
爹，要不要让我去看看？
Dad, do you want me to check?
女孩子要少管闲事
This is not a girl's business
这样吧，你先去探探他的底细
Well, you go and check his background
看看他究竟是什么来头
Find out where he is from
张老弟，不如你喝一杯
Brother Zhang, come have a drink
等一会儿再干活也不迟嘛
Take a break first
好
Okay
柳大哥，我陪你喝一杯就是
Brother Da Fu, let's have a drink
老弟，你到我们寨上也快一个月
You've been here for almost a month
我有一句话一直想问你
There's something I always want to ask you
什么话？
What is it?
你真的叫张新？
Is Zhang Xin your real name?
柳大哥，我当然叫张新
Brother Liu, Zhang Xin is my name for sure
您喝，我去赶工
You carry on, I've to get back to my work
你的手艺是跟谁学的？
From whom did you learn this skill?
我的手艺是给别人逼出来的
I was kind of forced to practice this skill
张老弟，我总觉得你有什么心事
Seems that you always have something on your mind
心事？
Something on my mind?
没有呀，我有什么心事？
No, nothing like that
你是有点特别
You are a bit strange
平时门也不出，话也不说
You don't go out, and you don't talk
小弟天性如此，装也装不出来
That's my nature, one's own personality
你会耍剑？
You know how to use a sword?
会不敢说，喜欢就是
Not really, I just like swords
柳大哥，莫非你怀疑我来路不正
Brother Liu, are you suspecting me?
哪里哪里，我只是随便说说的嘛
No, no... just asking
谁呀？
Who is it?
强盗来了
It's the bandits
老弟，还不快躲？想死呀？
Brother, hurry. Find a place to hide
夜劫柳家庄
You dare rob our village
你们是哪一路上的朋友？
Who are you?
老匹夫，你迟早会知道的
Old man, you will know sooner or later
往哪儿跑？
Where are you going?
好小子，你是个聋子？
Hey, are you deaf?
走
Let's go
快走，快…
Let's go, hurry...
奇怪
I don't understand
我一生从未亏待过江湖上的朋友
I've never been ungrateful to anyone
竟然有人劫庄
But someone has come to rob our village
我们庄上以往
Nothing like this happened
从来没有发生过这种事情
to our village in the past
听说庄上的人在谈论一件怪事
Everyone is talking about a strange thing now
什么怪事？
What is it?
我也是听说的
I heard that
说是庄上每户人家被抢劫
every house in our village was robbed
只有大虎的雕刻店…
Except Da Fu's stone carving shop...
你说这件事情与大虎有关？
You mean Da Fu is somehow related to the robbery?
他说的不是大虎
What he means is not Da Fu
那是谁？
Then who?
就是大虎店里那个叫张新的石工
Zhang Xin, the mason who works for Da Fu
是他？
That guy?
听说劫匪进了大虎的雕刻店
It's said that when the robbers got in Da Fu's shop
见了张新扭头就走
they left immediately on seeing Zhang Xin
有这种事？
Is that so?
你没瞧见大虎的店还是好好的？
Don't you see that Da Fu's shop is still in shape?
你是说他们见了张新就吓跑了？
You mean Zhang Xin scared them away?
不信你问问大虎
You can ask Da Fu
那是他亲眼看见的
He saw this with his own eyes
听说还有更神的呢
And there's something more strange
事情发生的时候
When the robbers came in
大虎躲在房里吓得半死
Da Fu was hiding inside the room and scared to death
张新一点也不害怕
But Zhang Xin was very calm
还在继续他的工作
He kept doing his work
你们说怪不怪？
Don't you think this is strange?
这小子可能跟劫匪有关系
This guy may have a connection with the robbers
就算没关系，也总有点什么来头
If he doesn't, he must have a background
要不然的话，他一定是个探子
Or he must be a spy
老弟，你…
Brother, you...
柳大哥，我走了
Brother Liu, I'm leaving
走？你是为了庄子人说你闲话？
Leaving? Because of the rumours in the village?
大家都说我跟那些劫匪有关系
Everyone says I've a connection with the robbers
你说我在这儿还能呆得下去吗？
Do you think I can stay here anymore?
柳大哥，还没做完的佛像
Brother Liu, the unfinished statue
就劳驾你把它去完成
please finish it for me
我也留不住你
So I can't stop you
我走了
I'm leaving
慢点
Wait
你就是张新？
Are you Zhang Xin?
是
Yes
总管，有什么吩咐？
Sir, how may I help?
没有什么，我们庄主想见见你
Our master wants to see you
庄主要见我？
He wants to see me?
是的，我有点事要找你
Oh yes, there's something I need you to do for me
您有什么吩咐？
What is it?
听说你的手艺很好
I've heard that you have very good skills
我们柳家祠堂需要一只炉鼎
And our ancestral temple needs a stone altar
想请你…
I wonder if...
庄主之命，小的不敢不从
I'd do whatever you want me to do
只是小的正要离开这儿
But it's just that I'm going to leave this place
啊，你要走了？
You're leaving?
为什么？
Why?
是不是听到什么闲话？
Is it because of the rumours?
假如是为了这一点的话
If this is the reason
你就更不能走
then you should stay here
你这么一走
Leaving just like that would mean
不就等于承认这件事
that you do admit
跟你有关系吗？
you have something to do with this robbery
我看你就再呆一段时间
I think you should continue staying here for some time
事情总会有个水落石出的
And we will find out the truth in due course
好吧，如果没有别的事
Well, if there's nothing else
小的就告辞了
then I better get going
请便
Okay
张新气宇不凡
There's something specially inspiring about Zhang Xin
以我看来他不是普普通通的人
I'm sure he's not an ordinary guy
他究竟是什么人迟早会知道的
Sooner or later we'll find out what he is
钟场主，干得好
Chief Zhong, well done
多谢教主夸奖
Thanks
先杀杀他的威风
Let's smash his power and prestige first
然后我再去找他算十年前那笔旧帐
Then I'll go take my revenge
不过那天晚上我们在庄上
But that night in the village
看到一个人，好像是丁梦豪
We saw a person who looked like Ding Menghao
什么？
What?
你说你看见失踪了几年的南剑？
The Southern Sword who went missing years ago?
不会的，假如是他
No, it couldn't be him. If that was him
你们还有命回来？
you wouldn't come back alive
门下也不敢确定
I am not sure either
不过也不是没有这个可能
But that's also possible
假如是他
If that's him
那真是踏破铁鞋无觅处
Then this will be my luck
得来全不费工夫？
to end my long and tough search
您要找他？
Are you looking for him?
难道我飞天蜈蚣就不配找他？
You think I'm not qualified for this?
柳小姐
Miss Liu
我只是想看看你的剑
I just want to take a look at your sword
我的剑跟别的剑没有什么不同
It's no different to the other blades
你既然有剑
Since you do have a sword
那天晚上为什么…
That night why didn't you...
不怕你笑话
It's a shame to tell the truth
我根本不会用剑
but I don't know how to use a sword
这把剑只是挂着玩的
I just hang it here for fun
说，你是谁？
Tell me, who are you?
柳小姐，你这是什么意思？
Miss Liu, what do you mean?
我终于试出你的功夫来
At last I hit upon a way to test your skills
假如你是普通人
If you were an ordinary person
绝不能进来得没有一点声息
you couldn't enter the room without making any noise
说，你是谁？
Tell me, who are you?
再不说，当心我刀下无情
If you don't speak, don't blame me
既然你为了试探我的武功而来
Since you're here to test my skills
那么我就告诉你
then let me tell you the truth
因为我被仇家追杀
I have enemies after me
只好躲到你们庄上来
So I came to hide in your village
那么你是一名剑手？
So you're a swordsman?
说不上是剑手
Not really
只是在江湖上浪荡浪荡就是
I'm just a wanderer
你既然有仇家追杀
If your enemies are after you
那光想躲是躲不掉
You can't just hide away
强盗来了…
The bandits are coming...
强盗
Bandits
怎么回事？
What's the matter?
就是这里
Over here
马家大杂院的人就是他
He's the one in the martial arts school of Ma village
下去看看
Let's go take a look
他就是躲到十八层地下
Even if he's hiding in hell
也把他找出来
we have to find him out
什么？又来了？
What? Here again?
那十几个人气势汹汹
Those several guys are coming fiercely
可能就是那班劫匪
They may be at the village now
好，去看看
Okay, let's go take a look
原来你在这儿
So you are here
您是…
You are...
你还记得吗？
Don't you remember?
上个月在马家大杂院武术馆里
Last month in the martial arts school of Ma village
毕帮主
Chief Bi
当时在下实在是无意杀少帮主
I didn't want to kill your son then
完全是…
It's because of...
是什么？
Of what?
朋友请了
My friend
阁下是…
You are...
老朽柳长风
I am Liu Changfeng
你就是神风剑客
So you are the Xinfeng Swordsman!
正是老朽
That's correct
阁下大概就是金剑帮的毕帮主了？
And you must be Chief Bi of the Golden Sword Clan
不敢
I am
帮主，来到荒庄有何见教？
Chief, what brings you to our small village?
我来找那小子
I've come looking for that guy
你跟他有仇？
You two have enmity?
他杀死了我的儿子
He killed my son
我到庄外去等你
I'll wait for you outside the village
一个时辰你不到
If you don't show up in two hours
柳兄
Brother Liu
我们只好再进庄向你要人了
Then I will come and ask you for this guy
走
Let's go
张新，这件事情
Zhang Xin, this time
我们实在无能为力
we can't offer much help
祸是你一个人闯的
You killed his son
也只好你一个人担当了
So you have to be responsible for this
你们放心，我不会连累大家
Don't worry, I won't get you into trouble
我们回去吧
Let's go home.
爹
Dad
走吧
Let's go
我说那小子不简单吧
I did say that guy is really something
仇家来找上他了
Now his enemy is here for him
在那儿？
Where?
在那儿
Over there
说不定上次劫庄那批家伙
Maybe those who robbed our village last time
就是来找他
actually came for him
他来了
He is here
客倌
Sir
伙计
Waiter
这人是谁？
Who is that guy?
对面雕刻店的石工
The mason of the stone carving shop
他的仇家来找他来了
His enemy is coming for him
这一去准没命
He won't come back alive
大爷里面请，马交我
Please come inside. I'll take care of the horse
小子，动手吧
Kid, come on
毕帮主，那天的事情
Chief Bi, even that day
在下的的确确实在不得已
I didn't have any say in the matter
拔剑
Draw your sword
自从误杀少帮主之后
After that unfortunate incident when your son died
在下发誓不再用剑
I swore never again to draw my sword
我不管你发什么誓
I don't care
我就知道报杀子之仇，动手吧
I just want revenge for my son. Let's fight
我不相信你有这般忍劲
Let's see how long can you tolerate
爹，如果张新他…
Dad, if Zhang Xin...
你管这干什么？
It's none of your concern, dear
那不是让张新去送死吗？
You're sending him to his death
可是金剑帮我们惹不起
The Golden Sword Clan rather not be our foes
再说这是他个人的事情
And moreover this is his personal matter
我们也犯不着…
We don't have to...
爹，我们总不能见死不救吧？
Dad, we can't just let him die, right?
拔剑吧，看来你是死定了
Take out your sword. You're dead
望帮主再明察
Chief, please forgive me
那可怪不了我了
Then don't blame me
好吧，既然你不想再用剑了
Okay, if you don't wish to use the sword anymore
那我就断了你的右臂
Then let me chop off your right arm
毕帮主，算了
Chief Bi, stop it
人家已经受你欺负够了
You've been bullying him enough
带你的剑手走吧
Leave with your men
你什么人？
Who are you?
这个你不需要问
You don't need to ask
你也不配知道
And you are not qualified to know
上
Get him
慢着，请壮士慢动手
Wait, please don't
通通给我上，上
All of you, attack
来吧，我的手也痒了
Come on, my arm is itching
朋友，我生平最看不惯这种事情
Pal, I simply can not tolerate this kind of thing
多谢兄台援手
Brother, thanks for your help
别客气，你贵姓？
Don't mention it. What's your name?
小的姓张，叫张新
My name is Zhang Xin
请教兄台贵姓？
How about you?
我叫邱一星
I am Qiu Yixing
北剑？
The Northern Sword?
在下就是北剑邱一星
Yes, I'm Qiu Yixing the Northern Sword
你受伤了？
Are you hurt?
没有
No
张兄，我先走一步
Brother Zhang, I have to go now
你的伤？
Are you alright?
不要紧，多谢小姐关心
I'm okay. Thank you, Miss
他们都是你杀的吗？
You killed them all?
不是，我哪有这种本事
No, I don't have such skill
是刚才那个人
It's that person
他是谁？
Who is he?
他是当代武林绝代剑手
He's a top swordsman
也算我有缘
I am really fortunate
能看到他出神入化的剑法
to witness his fantastic swordplay
刚才我真为你担心
I've been worrying about you
我们回去吧
Let's go home
他能逃命回来，邪不邪？
He comes back alive, what a surprise!
你懂什么？
What do you know?!
听说他向人家跪下瞌头
The word is he knelt down and kowtowed
才保住命的
to keep his life
要不然早被人家宰了
Otherwise he would be slain
你别损人
Don't slander people
我们张老弟只是不想出手
Brother Zhang just didn't want to fight
大虎，别吹了
Da Fu, stop boasting
都被人打成这样了还不想出手
He was beaten up and didn't want to fight back
天下会有这种事？
I don't think this is the case
朋友，你贵姓？
Pal, what's your name?
我叫大虎，加付碗筷来
I'm Da Fu. Bring him a bowl and a pair of chopsticks
来了
Coming
大虎，你在庄上住多久了？
Da Fu, how long have you been in this village?
生下来就在这儿
Since I was born
那你知不知道有个叫丁梦豪的
Do you know a person named Ding Menghao
住在庄上？
who lives in this village?
丁梦豪？没有
Ding Menghao? No
他在庄上多久了？
How long has he been here?
大约一个月
About a month
我们柳家庄外人很少，除了张新
We seldom have strangers here, except Zhang Xin
您找丁梦豪是不是一个石工？
This Ding Menghao... would he be a mason?
石工？
A mason?
说不定，也许他真的改行
Probably, he may have taken up a new profession
邱兄
Brother Qiu
是你？
It's you
你还没有走？
Still staying here?
我还有点私事没办完，你忙吗？
I have things to do. Are you busy now?
没什么
Not really
既然没事
In that case
上酒馆喝一杯吧
let's go and have a drink
这个…
I...
怎么，不肯赏脸？
What? Don't want to give me some face?
好
Okay
请
Please
邱兄到我们庄上来有什么事吗？
Brother Qiu, what brings you here?
想找个朋友
I am looking for a friend
找到了没有？
Have you found him yet?
找是找到了
I've found him
不过我那个朋友还不想见我
But he doesn't want to see me
张兄，我有两句话想跟你请教
Brother Zhang, I have something to ask you
邱兄有话尽管说吧
Brother Qiu, go ahead
我想问你
I just want to ask
你是不是拿我当朋友？
Do you treat me as a friend?
那还用说
Of course
邱兄对我的恩情我还没有报答呢
I haven't had a chance to repay your kindness
那么我想问你一句话
Then I want to ask you
你是不是丁梦豪？
Are you Ding Menghao?
你承认了？
So you are?
邱兄，你…
Brother Qiu, you...
丁梦豪，我找的人就是你
Ding Menghao, I am looking for you
一时大意，几乎错过了
I'm so careless, I almost missed you
邱兄，难道我有什么地方冒犯你
Brother Qiu, did I offend you in the past?
没有
No
那么究竟怎么回事？
Then why are you looking for me?
我要跟你比剑
I want to have a duel with you.
比剑？
A duel?
不错，你我被称为南北双剑
Yes, we are called Southern and Northern Swords
所谓一山不容二虎
No two tigers can live on one mountain
武林天下当然也不容有两个
So it means there can't be two top swordsmen
第一剑手
in this world
我们该决个胜负
We have to find out who is number one
邱兄
Brother Qiu
至少应该找出一个真正的第一剑
At least find out who is the true Fastest Sword
邱兄，小弟的剑法自信不如你
Brother Qiu, my skill is not better than you
邱兄才是天下第一剑手
You're indeed the top most swordsman in the world
天下第一剑手在我们比剑之后
We will find out who is the Fastest Sword
自有分论，怎么样？
after the duel, how's that?
我不能接受
I can't accept this
难道邱兄不把我当做朋友看待？
Don't you treat me as a friend?
我们交朋友是一回事
Being friends is one thing
决斗又是一回事
Having a duel is another
不过我已经发誓不再用剑
But I have sworn I'd never use a sword
你的决心我知道
I know of your determination
不过不出三天我会叫你答应
But you'll change your mind in three days
不会的，邱兄，告辞了
I sure hope not. Goodbye
我说
I tell you
总管，您有什么事吗？
What's the matter?
你们赶快早点收店
Close the shop as soon as possible
为什么？
Why?
照我的话做
Just do it
柳总管，出了什么事？
Mr. Liu, what happened?
你不知道庄主的旧仇人飞天蜈蚣
Master Liu's enemy Flying Centipede
要庄主亲自到旧城外赴约
wants to have a duel with him outside the village
要不然就要血洗柳庄
Otherwise he will kill everyone in our village
原来上次劫庄的就是他们
So it was them who robbed the village last time
你们赶快离开这儿
You better leave here now
留点神，我走了
Be careful. I have to go
丁兄
Brother Ding
这一次我看你不用剑是不行了
I think you have to use your sword again
飞天蜈蚣是不简单的
Flying Centipede is not an easy guy
柳长风，你还认得吴某人吗？
Liu, do you still remember me?
你想不到我还会活到今天吧？
You must be surprised that I'm still alive?
的确出我柳某人意料之外
Yes, I am really surprised
十年前你杀我于断魂崖
You wanted to kill me ten years ago
尊驾屠杀江湖人物心黑手辣
Because you had cruelly killed many people
我只不过是为天下人除害而已
And I just want to do a favour to the martial world
废话少说
Cut the crap
你死到临头，你知道吗？
You are going to die, don't you know that?
尊驾既然找我寻仇
If you want to have revenge on me
何以日前屠杀庄人？
why then did you kill my village folk before?
那是让你瞧瞧我的厉害
Just to let you see how powerful I am
柳长风，你亮刀吧
Liu, show your blade
让我来
Let me kill him
谁来都是一样，你们跑不了
You can't escape from me
上
Fight
好小子，你找死？
Kid, you want to die?
飞天蜈蚣，带着你的人回去吧
Flying Centipede, leave with your men
原来你就是那个姓丁的？
So you are that guy named Ding?
你来干什么？
What are you doing here?
我来表示我的清白，那次劫庄
I want to prove my innocence. The robbers...
我知道跟你无关，快走
I know you have nothing to do with them. Leave now
来，我飞天蜈蚣向你领教
Come on, let's see how good you are
还不滚
Get away
快走…
Let's go...
慢走
Wait
你到底是谁？
Who are you really?
他就是名震天下的南剑丁梦豪
He is the famous Southern Sword, Ding Menghao
好个丁梦豪
Well, Ding Menghao
你竟然骗我说什么被仇家追杀
The other day you lied that you're pursued by enemy
跑到我们庄上来隐居
and sought shelter in our village
柳小姐，在下…
Miss Liu, I...
别在下在上，我讨厌人家骗我
Stop it, I hate people lying to me
丁兄，我们该动手了吧
Brother Ding, we should have a duel now
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是邱一星
I am Qiu Yixing
北剑？
The Northern Sword?
二位大侠莅临荒庄
We have two famous heroes in our village
请恕老朽有眼无珠
Please forgive my ignorance
今日若非丁兄相救
If we didn't have Brother Ding here to help
老朽及庄人恐怕…
My village and I would be...
有南剑在，你们还怕什么？
The Southern Sword is here, you shouldn't be afraid
丁兄，动手吧
Brother Ding, let's have a fight
动手？
A fight?
我找他比剑
I want to have a duel with him
比剑？
A duel?
常言道二虎相争必有一伤
When two tigers fight, one is bound to be hurt
二位何必呢？
So why insist on this?
我要是不跟他斗出个
I want to have a duel with him to find out
谁是天下第一剑手
who is the top most swordsman in the world
我活着还有什么意义？
Otherwise my life will be meaningless
丁兄
Brother Ding
邱兄
Brother Qiu
小弟已经决心不再跟人家比剑
I've decided never to have a duel with other people
你怕死？
Are you afraid of death?
懦夫
Coward
也好
Fine
我只好用别的办法叫你斗剑
I'll figure out another way to make you have a duel
失陪
See you
柳大哥
Brother Liu
刚才姓邱的来过
That Qiu fellow was here a while back
他用剑劈毁了这些东西
He destroyed everything with his sword
他欺人太甚
This is too much
老弟，这到底是怎么回事？
Brother, what is this all about?
你们不是朋友吗？怎么会…
I thought you guys are friends! How come...
柳大哥，都是我连累你
Brother Liu, it's all my fault
丁大侠，丁大侠，不好了
Mr. Ding, something happened
怎么回事？
What's the matter?
我们小姐给人家劫走了
Our miss is kidnapped
真有这回事？
Really?
当然真的
That's true
一定是他
It must be him
邱一星，你好卑鄙的家伙
Qiu Yixing, you are despicable
你不要动怒
Don't get angry, if you promise to have a duel
你答应动手，捣毁的东西我照赔
I'll pay for everything I've broken
你为什么劫走柳小姐？
Why kidnap Miss Liu?
柳小姐被人劫走？
Miss Liu has been kidnapped?
别装蒜了
Don't play dumb
丁兄，我邱一星生平为人
Brother Ding, I dare not claim
不敢说怎么正直
I am a man of integrity
但至少不会对女人下手
But at least I won't harm a woman
一定是他
It must be him
谁呀？
Who?
我知道劫走柳小姐的是谁
I know who'd have kidnapped Miss Liu
你要我告诉你，可以
I can tell you, no problem
不过条件是你要跟我比剑
But you must have a duel with me
好，你说
Okay, tell me
那么我们走
Then let's go
就是他
It's him
丁大侠，我知道你会来的
Mr. Ding, I knew you would come
是你劫走柳小姐？
You kidnapped Miss Liu?
不错
Right
为什么？
Why?
对了，丁大侠
Mr. Ding
一个月前你杀死了我弟弟
You've killed my younger brother a month ago
黑蛇剑客
The Black Snake Swordsman
我弟弟剑法除了南北双剑之外
He had very good sword skills. Only the
敢说没有敌手
Southern and Northern Swords are better than him
而当时北剑邱一星
And there was no way the Northern Sword
不可能来到南方
could come to the south at that time
所以我断定你杀死了我弟弟
So it must be you who killed my brother
我根本没有杀你的弟弟
I didn't kill your brother
还赖？
You're still denying
慢，白蛇剑客，你找错了人了
Wait, White Snake, you've got the wrong guy
你弟弟是我杀死的
I killed your brother
我是北剑邱一星
I'm Qiu Yixing, the Northern Sword
在路上我杀死了黑蛇剑客
I've killed Black Snake on the road
把剑收起来
Retrieve your sword
柳小姐呢？
Where's Miss Liu?
在关帝庙里
In the temple
不过我死了她也完了
But if I died, she'll die too
我给她吃了一种药
I've fed her some poison
又是这一套
It's not a new trick
起来
Get up
什么事？
What?
我要你死得瞑目
I want you to die in peace
解药一定在他身上
He must be carrying the antidote
我先到关帝庙去
I'm going to the temple now
清儿，清儿
Qing Er...
赶快给她喝解药
Give her the antidote now
丁兄，柳小姐已经找到了
Brother Ding, we've found Miss Liu
你曾经答应过我的
And the matter you've promised me
现在？
Now?
废话
Bullshit
你听我说
Listen!
不必多说
Enough
明天一早我在这儿等你
I'll be waiting here for you tomorrow
来了，他来了
He's coming
你们不要进来
Don't go inside
总有一个会出来的
One of us will come out at last
丁兄果然没有令我失望
So you've come eventually
丁兄，邱某领教了
Brother Ding, I want to learn from you
邱兄，咱们既然结为知己
Brother Qiu, since we are friends
你昨天答应我的
You've promised me yesterday
是的
Right
不过老兄又何必苦苦相逼呢？
But why are you so persistent about the duel?
你是不知道找你比剑，分个高下
It's all about finding out who is the best
是我邱一星这一生最大的愿望
This is the only wish in my life
拔剑
Draw your sword
邱兄，兄弟对剑刀荒废已久
Brother Qiu, I haven't practiced for a long time
甘拜下风
I admit defeat
丁梦豪
Ding Menghao
你连剑都不出鞘就说这种风凉话
You say so when your sword is still in the sheath
岂不是存心侮辱我吗？
Are you trying to insult me?
不，这是梦豪肺腑之言
No, I speak from my heart
邱兄千万不要误会
Brother Qiu, don't take me wrong
误会？
Take you wrong?
我告诉你，今天你非动剑不可了
You have to use your sword today
看剑
Watch out
你是不是非动手是不行了
You have to use your sword this time
邱兄，我们还要比吗？
Brother Qiu, do we still have to fight?
少废话，拔剑
Quit beating around the bush, now out with your sword
不用了，我已经输了
No, I've lost already
不，你剑不出鞘，我不能算赢
No, your sword is still in the sheath. I didn't win
你一定要看我的剑？
So you have to see my sword?
久闻丁兄手上所拿的
I've heard that your sword
是把七星名剑
is a rare treasure
好吧，那么我就让你看看
Okay, I'll let you have a look
断剑
A broken sword
邱兄，这就是我不再用剑的决心
Brother Qiu, this is the proof of my determination
那我的剑就不能比你的长
Then my sword can't be longer than yours
好，现在我们该动手了
Okay, we should start now
太大
It's still too big
丁梦豪，上天下地
Ding Menghao, wherever you go
今天你是逃不了
You can't escape today
再小一点
Make it smaller
怎么办？
What should we do?
让我们来
Let us do it
请问老丈，有一个叫丁梦豪的
Old sir, is there a person named Ding Menghao
是不是在你们寨上？
living in your village?
你找他干什么？
Why are you looking for him?
比剑
To have a duel
比剑？
A duel?
他已经死了
He's already dead
死了？
He died?
昨天他跟北剑邱一星比剑
Yesterday he had a duel with the Northern Sword
他们都死了
They both died
你看，现在正在下葬
See, that's their funeral
我来迟了一步
Guess I'm a little late
"The grave of Ding Menghao and Qiu Yixing"
谢谢你父亲想出这个办法
I'm truly grateful for your father's wonderful idea
这是庄人的意思
It's the unanimous decision of all the villagers here
他们都希望你留下
They all want you to stay
这样别人就以为
The other people will thus think
你真的跟北剑一起死了
that you died together with the Northern Sword
今后再不会有人找你比剑
And no one will again seek you to have a duel
"The grave of Ding Menghao"